A Guide to the Making of Virginia Architecture Collection, 1988-1994
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Making of Virginia Architecture Collection 1988-1994
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 383
4 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Special Collections and Archives in December 2009 by Dr. Charles Brownell.
Biographical/Historical Information
The book, or catalogue, "The Making of Virginia Architecture", was published in 1992 and co-authored by Charles E. Brownell, Calder Loth, William M. S. Rasmussen, and Richard Guy Wilson. The genesis of the project occurred years earlier, when the authors concluded that Virginia's principal artistic achievement was architecture, and decided to write a catalogue that documented the range and variety of architecture in Virginia.
The book was a companion to the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts exhibition entitled The Making of Virginia Architecture: Drawings and Models, 1719-1990, which ran November 10, 1992 to January 3, 1993. The original VMFA exhibition name was alternatively referred to as "Architectural Drawing in Virginia" and "Virginia's Architectural Drawing" (VAD), and the exhibition was postponed in 1988 and 1990; hence references in the collection to these different names, abbreviations, and dates.
For their publication, the authors were presented with the Architectural Exhibition Catalogue Award in 1993 by The Society of Architectural Historians "in recognition of its excellence, having been judged the outstanding catalogue of an architectural history exhibition published in 1992".
Scope and Content
Records were collected from 1988 to 1994 by Dr. Brownell in the course of researching and writing the book, and preparing for the exhibition. The bulk of the material consists of notes and correspondence related to chapter 6 of the book, "The Survey: A Selection of Virginia Architectural Drawings, Studies, Models 1719-1990". This chapter contains detailed histories and architectural plans of Virginia buildings and monuments. Folder names beginning with "catalogue entry" refer to entries in chapter 6, and correspond either to the buildings themselves or to their designers.
The collection includes drafts of Dr. Brownell's Chapter 2, "Laying the Groundwork: The Classical Tradition and Virginia Architecture, 1770-1870", and his contribution to Chapter 4 (Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870"). There are chapter drafts by William M. S. Rasmussen and Richard Guy Wilson as well.
The collection contains correspondence among the authors and institutional curators regarding loan requests for the VMFA exhibition. Museum and repository sources used for both the book and exhibition are also included.
Arrangement
Materials in the collection are arranged according to their original order.
Contents List
- MVA catalogue award presented by The Society of Architectural Historians 1993 (Box-folder 1:1)
- United States Capitol and President's House 1792 competition drawings 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Acknowledgements 1990-1992 (Box-folder 1:3)
- General Bibliography 1992 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Catalogue entry data sheet 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Vernacular architecture 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Catalogue entry of Belle Farm (18th century architecture) 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Catalogue entry of Amelia County Courthouse (18th century architecture) 1991 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Catalogue entries of 18th century architectural drawings 1988-1990 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Catalogue entry of Menokin (18th century architecture) 1990-1991, 1995-1996, 2001 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Catalogue entry of Mount Vernon (18th century architecture) 1989-1998 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Catalogue entry of Newmarket (18th century architecture) 1990-1992 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Catalogue entry of Skipwith (18th century architecture) 1992 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Jefferson, pre-Europe (old draft) 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Jefferson, after Europe (old draft) 1990 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Jefferson (old draft) 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Jefferson: 1 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Jefferson: 2 1989-1992 [folder 1 of 2] (Box-folder 1:18)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Jefferson: 2 1989-1992 [folder 2 of 2] (Box-folder 1:19)
- Catalogue entries of non-graphic artifacts 1988, 1992 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Catalogue entry of Bremo Recess 1988, 1991 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Sources (19th century architecture) 1988 (Box-folder 1:22)
- Catalogue entry of Sweet Briar House (19th century architecture) 1991 (Box-folder 1:23)
- Catalogue entry of Samuel Boates (19th century architecture) 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1:24)
- Catalogue entry of N. Le Brun (19th century architecture) 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1:25)
- Catalogue entry of E. G. Lind (19th century architecture) 1988 (Box-folder 1:26)
- Catalogue entry of Robert Cary Long, Jr., (19th century architecture) 1988, 1991 (Box-folder 1:27)
- Catalogue entry of Albert Lybrock (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1:28)
- Catalogue entry of John McComb 1991 (Box-folder 1:29)
- Catalogue entry of Charles Augustus Busby 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Catalogue entry of John Buchanan Danforth (19th century architecture) 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Catalogue entry of Alexander Jackson Davis (19th century architecture) 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Catalogue entry of George Aloysius Frederick (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Catalogue entry of Maximilian Godefroy (19th century architecture) 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Drawings of John Haviland, request for inclusion in VMFA MVA exhibition 1991 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Catalogue entries of later 19th century architecture 1988-1990 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Catalogue entry of Benjamin Henry Latrobe 1990-1992 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Catalogue entry of John McComb, Jr. 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Catalogue entry of Robert Mills 1988-1989-, 1991 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Catalogue entries of monuments: I 1988 (Box-folder 2:11)
- Catalogue entries of monuments: II 1988 (Box-folder 2:12)
- Catalogue entry of John Notman (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:13)
- Catalogue entry of Alexander Parris 1988-1991 (Box-folder 2:14)
- Catalogue entry of Calvin Pollard (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:15)
- Catalogue entries of revivals 1988 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Catalogue entry of Alfred L. Rives (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:17)
- Catalogue entry of P. Slaughter 1989 (Box-folder 2:18)
- Catalogue entry of Norris G. Starkweather (19th century architecture) 1988, 1991 (Box-folder 2:19)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas S. Stewart (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:20)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Alexander Tefft (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:21)
- Catalogue entry of John Rochester Thomas (19th century architecture) 1988-1991 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Catalogue entry of Thomas Ustick Walter (19th century architecture) 1988, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:23)
- Catalogue entry of Ammi B. Young (19th century architecture) 1990 (Box-folder 2:24)
- Catalogue entries by Calder Loth and William Rasmussen (MVA co-authors), [Includes entries of Richard King, Edmund George Lind, John Neilson, Samuel McDowell Reid, William T. Murdoch & William Richards] 1991 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Letter from Richard Guy Wilson to William Rasmussen (MVA co-authors) 1991 (Box-folder 2:26)
- Correspondence 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2:27)
- Correspondence 1990-1994 (Box-folder 2:28)
- Brownell discoveries of materials and documentation 1991 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Proposal for exhibition compact disc presentation 1991 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Catalogue illustrations to Chapter 2, "Laying the Groundwork: The Classical Tradition and Virginia Architecture, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Chapter 2, "Laying the Groundwork: The Classical Tradition and Virginia Architecture, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: "Draft to recycle" 1991 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Chapter 1, "Drafting the Plans: Pride and Practicality in Virginia's Colonial Architecture, 1715-1770" by William M. S. Rasmussen: correspondence 1991 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Chapter 4, Part 3, "Drawings, Models, and the Making of Architecture in Virginia Since 1870" by Richard Guy Wilson: Draft 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Catalogue labels 1990-1992 (Box-folder 3:7)
- Correspondence: Exhibition loan requests for drawings 1990 (Box-folder 3:8)
- Lists of drawings for exhibition 1988-1991 (Box-folder 3:9)
- Format guidelines for catalogue entries 1989-1991 (Box-folder 3:10)
- Fellowship and grants sources 1988 (Box-folder 3:11)
- Glossary drafts 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:12)
- The "eleventh hour" 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3:13)
- Inquiry into architectural drawings at the Winterthur Museum for MVA exhibition 1989-1990 (Box-folder 3:14)
- Inquiry into photographs of architectural drawings at the Valentine Richmond History Center 1989 (Box-folder 3:15)
- Requests for photographs of architectural drawings from the New York Historical Society for MVA exhibition 1989-1991 (Box-folder 3:16)
- Loan requests for / inquiries about drawings and photographs at New York repositories for MVA exhibition 1988-1989 (Box-folder 3:17)
- Inquiry into architectural drawings and photographs at New Haven, Connecticut repositories 1988 (Box-folder 3:18)
- Loan and permission requests from the Maryland Historical Society for MVA exhibition 1989-1991 (Box-folder 3:19)
- Loan requests for drawings and photographs from the Massachusetts Historical Society for MVA exhibition 1989-1990 (Box-folder 3:20)
- Catalogue illustrations 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:21)
- Catalogue illustrations: color plates 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3:22)
- Exhibition expenditures, statements, and contracts 1988-1991, 1993 (Box-folder 3:23)
- Board of advisors / Honorary Committee 1988, 1990 (Box-folder 3:24)
- MVA exhibition gallery handout 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:25)
- Catalogue illustrations to Chapter 4, Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: spares undated (Box-folder 3:26)
- Catalogue illustrations to Chapter 4, Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:27)
- Chapter 4, Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: Draft 1 and documents 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3:28)
- Chapter 4, Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: Draft 1 1991 (Box-folder 3:29)
- Chapter 4, Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: Draft 3 1991 (Box-folder 3:30)
- Chapter 4, Part 2, "Architectural Drawings and Design, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: "Obsolete" 1991 (Box-folder 3:31)
- Chapter 2, "Laying the Groundwork: The Classical Tradition and Virginia Architecture, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: Draft 1991 (Box-folder 3:32)
- Chapter 2, "Laying the Groundwork: The Classical Tradition and Virginia Architecture, 1770-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: Draft 4 1991 (Box-folder 3:33)
- Exhibition letter of inquiry 1988 (Box-folder 3:34)
- Essay, "The Classical Tradition and Virginia, 1715-1870" by Charles E. Brownell: excerpt from MVA catalogue, Chapter 2, for use in his UVA course, "Early American Architecture", Fall 1991 1991 (Box-folder 3:35)
- Chapter 4 figure captions 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:36)
- Chapter 4, Part 1, "Architectural Drawings and Design in the Virginia Colony", Draft 1992 (Box-folder 3:37)
- Chapter 1 figure captions 1992 (Box-folder 3:38)
- Chapter 2 figure captions 1992 (Box-folder 3:39)
- Chapter 1, "Setting the Plan: Pride and Practicality in Virginia's Colonial Architecture, 1719-1770" by William M.S. Rasmussen: Draft [note: title later changed to "Drafting the Plans"] 1991 (Box-folder 3:40)
- Chapter 6 survey numbers 1 through 13, Draft 1991 (Box-folder 3:41)
- Chapter 6 survey numbers 14 through 27 1991 (Box-folder 3:42)
- Chapter 6 survey numbers 28 through 50 1991 (Box-folder 3:43)
- Chapter 6 survey numbers 51 through 55 1991 (Box-folder 3:44)
- Exhibition planning meetings 1986-1992 (Box-folder 3:45)
- National Endowment for the Humanities and National Endowment for the Arts exhibition grant requests 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3:46)
- Exhibition prospectus 1988-1989, 1991 (Box-folder 3:47)
- Exhibition publicity 1992 (Box-folder 3:48)
- Exhibition query submission to periodicals 1988-1989 (Box-folder 3:49)
- Repository sources 1989 (Box-folder 3:50)
- Repository sources, "Checked" 1988 (Box-folder 3:51)
- Repository sources, "To check" 1988-1989 (Box-folder 3:52)
- Orders for exhibition prints 1988 (Box-folder 3:53)